Guide to the James W. Ford Papers and Photographs TAM.588
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
James W. Ford Papers and Photographs
1920s-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bryant, Solliah
Ford, James W., 1893-1957
TAM.588
0.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes.
James W. Ford (1893-1957) was a prominent African American Communist of Jamaican origin and the vice-presidential candidate of the Communist Party in 1932, 1936, and 1940. He was a delegate to the Profintern Congress in Moscow in 1928, organized the first International Conference of Negro Workers in Hamburg, Germany in 1930, and became the editor of the Negro Worker, published by the International Trade Union Committee of Negro Workers, established at the Conference. After World War II his role in the Party diminished, however, he chaired the Bedford-Stuyvesant Party organization, and was executive director of the National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership, a Party group set up to support Smith Act defendants. The papers include correspondence, inclcuding items from Ralph Bunche, Jr., W.E.B. Du Bois, and Paul Robeson, memorabilia, including registration cards for international Communist conferences, obituaries and condolence cards sent to his widow Reba, and a specially bound personal copy of his book The Negro and the Democratic Front (1938). The photographs include a group shot of notable Communists taken in Spain during the Spanish Civil War, Angelo Herndon being carried on the shoulders of Ford and others, images of Communist conferences, of Ford in Mexico, campaigning in 1936, head shots and family portraits.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by the Tamiment Library from Solliah Bryant in 2011. The accession number associated with this collection is 2011.108.
Arrangement
Orangized into two alphabetically arranged series:
Series I, Papers
Series II, Photographs.
Historical/Biographical Note
James W. Ford (1893-1957) was a prominent African American Communist of Jamaican origin and the vice-presidential candidate of the Communist Party in 1932, 1936, and 1940. He was a delegate to the Profintern Congress in Moscow in 1928, organized the first International Conference of Negro Workers in Hamburg, Germany in 1930, and became the editor of the Negro Worker, published by the International Trade Union Committee of Negro Workers, established at the Conference. After World War II his role in the Party diminished, however, he chaired the Bedford-Stuyvesant Party organization, and was executive director of the National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership, a Party group set up to support Smith Act defendants.
Scope and Content Note
The papers include correspondence, inclcuding items from Charlotta Bass, Ralph Bunche, Jr., W.E.B. Du Bois, Ferdinand Smith and Paul Robeson, a telegram from Cyril Briggs of the Crusder News Service to Ford in Paris, requesting he go to Spain to write a series of articles on the Spanish Civil War, a letter of introduction from the French Communist Party to the Spanish Communist Party, memorabilia, including registration cards for international Communist conferences, including the 6th Congress of the Communist International (1928), the 5th Congress of the Red International of Labor Unions (1930), the Conference International pour l'Enfance Africaine (1931), obituaries and condolence cards sent to his widow Reba, the text of a speech by William Patterson given at Ford's funeral, and a specially bound personal copy of his book The Negro and the Democratic Front (1938). The photographs include a group shot of notable Communists taken in Spain during the Spanish Civil War, including Harry Haywood and Robert Minor, a picture of Angelo Herndon being carried on the shoulders of Ford and others, images from Communist conferences, of Ford in Mexico, campaigning in 1936, head shots and family portraits.
Identity cards.; Obituaries.; African American communists -- History; Communism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Greeting cards.; Photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- African Americans; Correspondence.; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971; Jones, Claudia, 1915-1964.; Ford, Reba; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Haywood, Harry, 1898-1985; Smith, Ferdinand; Briggs, Cyril V. (Cyril Valentine), 1888-1966; Bryant, Solliah; Ford, James W., 1893-1957; Bryant, Solliah
- Papers
  - Biographical Clippings, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Briggs, Cyril (Crusader News Service): Telegram to JWF [in Paris] "Request you proceed Madrid immediately series articles Negro angle Spanish struggle..., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bunche, Ralph, Jr.: Letters (2) to JWF [in Mexico City] on letterhead of the Carnegie-Myrdal Study, Feb 26, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Death: Condolence Card from Dr, and Mrs, W.E. Burghardt Du Bois, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3A)
  - Death: Condolence Cards and Letters, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Death: Condolence Cards and Letters from Notables (Communists, Others), including Herbert Aptheker, James Aronson, Charlotta Bass, Claudia Jones, John Pittman, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Death: Condolence Telegrams, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Death: Obituaries, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Death: Poems Sent to Reba Ford (widow), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Death: Unity Funeral Home Register, Memorial Serive (Includes text of speech by William Patterson), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dictionary of American Negro Biography Entry for JWF, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership Cards: Jamaican Organizations, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership Ticket: Conference Internationale pour L"Enfance Africaine [Paris], 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Negro and the Democratic Front [Disbound copy of book by JWF with notes on first page], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Negro and the Democratic Front [Specially Harbound Personal Copy], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Negro and the Imperialist War, 1914-1918 [pamphlet by JWF], 1929 (Box 1, Folder 14A)
  - Negro Marxists Statement (Draft) on William Z. Foster's 75th Birthday, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Parti Communiste Francais: Letter Introducing For to the Parti Communiste Espagnol, Apr 28, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Registration Card: 5th Congress Profintern (Red International of Labor Unions (Moscow), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Registration Cards: 6th Congress, Communist International (Moscow), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Robeson, Paul: "Dear Jim and Reba [Thank you note]...feeling better...., Nov 14, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Smith, Ferdinand: Letter from, Jan 3, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photographs
  - Angelo Herndon Being Carried on Shoulders of JWF, Others, Upon Return from Georgia Trial, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Denver, Colorado: Union Station (Riding in Car during Vice-Presidential Campaign), Oct 16, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family, Biographical (7 images), 1921-1950s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Framed Group Portrait: Includes, in addition to JWF, Israel Amter, Bill Lawrence [In Restaurant: Spanish Civil War-related Lunch Event], Nov, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Framed Portrait: JWF In His Office, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Framed Group Portrait: Mexico, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (In Germany), 1928-1930 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Group Portrait [In USSR, including several Black individuals], circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Head Shots (3), Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - JWF in Mexico [Writing, with two white persons in background, circa 1938-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Day of Bulgaria Reception, Sep 10, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Postal Workers [Integrated] Baseball Team: Chicago Champions, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Spain Group Portrait [2" x 2"]: One image listing [Harry Haywood, [Robert] Minor, [Harry McKelvey White], Bates, JWF., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)